<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[In The Aggregate]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexgmcm.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexgmcm.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-14T15:09:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexgmcm.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[alexgmcm]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[All Your Base64 Are Belong to Us]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexgmcm.github.io/blog/2014/12/13/all-your-base64-are-belong-to-us/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T10:00:36+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexgmcm.github.io/blog/2014/12/13/all-your-base64-are-belong-to-us</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently found the <a href="http://cryptopals.com/">Matasano Crypto Challenges</a> and eagerly set about solving the first one - converting a hex string to base64. My code can <a href="https://github.com/alexgmcm/MatasanoCrypto/tree/master/1">be found here.</a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Hex (short for hexadecimal) is the base 16 number system, so whereas decimal has 10 symbols representing the values from 0 to 9, hexadecimal has 16 representing the values 0 to 15. It uses the numbers 0-9 for 0-9 and then the letters a-f for 10-15. Base64 on the other hand has 64 symbols representing the values 0 to 63 (A-Z representing 0-25, a-z representing 26-51, 0-9 representing 52-61 and + and / representing 62 and 63 respectively)</p>

<p>Any number can be represented in any base as a polynomial. For example we can represent any number, \(N_{16}\) ,in base 16 (hexadecimal) as the following:</p>

<p>\[ N&#95;{16} = \sum&#95;{i} a&#95;{i} 16^i \]</p>

<p>where \(a_i\) is some integer between 0 and 15.</p>

<p>Similarly we may represent a number in Base64 as:</p>

<p>\[ N&#95;{64} = \sum&#95;{j} b&#95;{j} 64^j = \sum&#95;{j} b&#95;{j} 16^j 4^j \]</p>

<p>If we are representing the same number (i.e. we are converting between bases) then we can equate these two:</p>

<p>\[ N = \sum&#95;{j} b&#95;{j} 16^j 4^j = \sum&#95;{i} a&#95;{i} 16^i \]</p>

<p>We wish to convert from base 16 to base 64. The representation of a number in a higher base can only be smaller or at most the same size (in terms of the length of the string required to represent it, i.e. the values of i or j) as the representation in the original lower base.</p>

<p>This means that if we start at the most significant digit of the hex string we can imagine that at most there will be a digit equivalent to it in the base64 string and then we can equate i and j and calculate the value of that digit. Therefore for that digit, we obtain:</p>

<p>\[ b&#95;{i} 16^i 4^i = a&#95;{i} 16^i \]
\[ \therefore b&#95;{i}  = \frac{a&#95;{i}}{4^i}  \]</p>

<p>But the values of a and b must be integers within the range of representation of their respective bases - in this case it is important to us that b is an integer, we know that it will always be less than 64 because we are starting with the most significant digit and converting to a lower base so the problem will be carrying the decimal remainder to the lower digits rather than carrying the modulo 64 remainder to higher digits. This is confusing to discuss in the abstract but will be clearly demonstrated by an example.</p>

<p>Let us consider the hex string &#39;2af3&#39; which is equal to 10995 in decimal. We start with the most significant digit which is 2. It is the 4th digit and therefore using our polynomial representation we have i=3, as i=0 for the first digit. Therefore from the above arguments we calculate:</p>

<p>\[ \frac{2}{4^3} = \frac{1}{32} \]</p>

<p>Therefore the integer part is zero, so the base64 value for this digit is zero, represented by A. To carry the remainder along to the next digit we multiply the decimal part by 64 and then add it to the next digit.</p>

<p>\[ \frac{1}{32} \cdot 64 = 2 \]</p>

<p>Therefore the following digit has the value:</p>

<p>\[ 2 + \frac{10}{4^2} \]</p>

<p>The 2 comes from the carry and the 10 from the fact that the next digit is &#39;a&#39; which represents a value of 10 in the hex number system.</p>

<p>The integer part of this is 2, represented in base64 as C, so the first digit in our base 64 string is C. Then we repeat the carry process as before:
\[\frac{10}{4^2} \cdot 64 = 40 \]</p>

<p>Thus the value of the next digit is:</p>

<p>\[40+\frac{15}{4} = 43 + \frac{3}{4}\]</p>

<p>The representation of 43 in base64 is r. And then we carry over the decimal part as before:
\[\frac{3}{4}\cdot 64 = 48\]</p>

<p>Thus we get the value of the final digit to be:</p>

<p>\[ 48+ 3 = 51\]</p>

<p>51 is represented as z in base 64 and thus the representation of the hex string 2af3 is Crz in base64, note that the string we obtained was ACrz but we strip the leading zeroes (which are represented by A).</p>

<p>This result can be confirmed by quickly checking that the decimal representations agree:
\[ (2 \times 64^2) + (43 \times 64) + 51 = (2 \times 16^3) + (10 \times 16^2) + (15 \times 16) + 3 = 10995 \]</p>

<p>I had some difficulty with insufficient precision when using the standard Python float types and so I used the Decimal class from the decimal module which allows arbritary precision floating point calculations.</p>

<!--- _ = &#95; --->
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It Is an ex-Classic. It Has Ceased to Be...]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexgmcm.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/it-is-an-ex-classic-it-has-ceased-to-be-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-22T00:05:54+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexgmcm.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/it-is-an-ex-classic-it-has-ceased-to-be-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&#8230;And on the pedestal these words appear:<br/>&#8216;My name is Ozymandias, king of kings:<br/>Look on my works, ye Mighty, and despair!&#8217;<br/>Nothing beside remains. Round the decay<br/>Of that colossal wreck, boundless and bare<br/>The lone and level sands stretch far away.</p><footer><strong>Percy Bysshe Shelly</strong> <cite>Ozymandias (1818)</cite></footer></blockquote>

<p>As mentioned in the <a href="http://alexgmcm.github.io/about">About page</a> the name of the blog comes from a passage in <em>The Sign of the Four</em> by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Winwood Reade is good upon the subject,&#8221; said Holmes. &#8220;He remarks that, while the individual man is an insoluble puzzle, in the aggregate he becomes a mathematical certainty. You can, for example, never foretell what any one man will do, but you can say with precision what an average number will be up to. Individuals vary, but percentages remain constant. So says the statistician.&#8221;</p><footer><strong>Sir Arthur Conan Doyle</strong> <cite>The Sign of the Four (1890)</cite></footer></blockquote>

<!-- more -->

<p>Sherlock Holmes is referring to Winwood Reade&#39;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Winwood_Reade#The_Martyrdom_of_Man_.281872.29"><em>The Martyrdom of Man</em></a>. Apparently it was one of the most prominent books of the day -  offering a secular, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freethought">Freethinking</a> perspective on history.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.exclassics.com/martyrdom/mrtintro.htm">full text</a> is freely available at the wonderful <a href="http://www.exclassics.com/">exclassics.com</a> along with other forgotten relics such as:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.exclassics.com/dwarf/dwarfint.htm"><em>The Memoirs of Jozef Borowlaski, The Last Court Dwarf</em></a> - apparently he was sort of like a real-life Tyrion Lannister.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.exclassics.com/richard/richint.htm"><em>The History of King Richard the Third</em>, by Thomas More</a> - learn just <em>how</em> he ended up <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-leicestershire-21063882">beneath a Leicester car park!</a></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.exclassics.com/espoke/espkint.htm"><em>English as She is Spoke</em>, by Pedro Carolino and Jose da Fonseca</a> - a Portuguese/English phrase book written by authors who knew no English and thus constructed the book by taking a Portuguese/French phrasebook and translating the French word for word into English using a dictionary. 
What could possibly go wrong? Well, here&#39;s an example:
<blockquote><p><strong>Very dissatisfied customer (brandishing pistol):</strong> Here is a horse who have a bad looks. Give me another; I will not that. He not sall know to march, he is pursy, he is foundered. Don&#39;t you are ashamed to give me a jade as like? he is undshoed, he is with nails up; it want to lead to the farrier.</p><p><strong>Terrified horse dealer:</strong> Your pistols are its loads?</p></blockquote>
One can only presume they went on to produce a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirty_Hungarian_Phrasebook">Hungarian phrasebook</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_your_base_are_belong_to_us">translate video games</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.exclassics.com/beeton/beetintr.htm"><em>The Book of Household Management</em> by Mrs. Isabella Beeton</a> - experience the Delia Smith of the Victorian era. Who can resist such delicious treats as <a href="http://www.exclassics.com/beeton/beet27.htm#P1251"><em>Very Plain Bread Pudding</em></a> or <a href="http://www.exclassics.com/beeton/beet6.htm#P165"><em>Useful Soup for Benevolent Purposes</em></a>!?
She also makes the rather unlikely claim that:
<blockquote><p>The shepherds of Egypt had a singular manner of cooking eggs without the aid of fire. They placed them in a sling, which they turned so rapidly that the friction of the air heated them to the exact point required for use.</p></blockquote>
Perhaps I&#39;ll make a post calculating just how fast one would have to spin the sling&#8230;</p></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Basket Case]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexgmcm.github.io/blog/2014/11/20/basket-case/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-20T17:22:47+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexgmcm.github.io/blog/2014/11/20/basket-case</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>When you have eliminated the impossible, whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.</p><footer><strong>Sherlock Holmes</strong></footer></blockquote>

<p>I recently discovered a neat problem while looking at job applications. From the <a href="http://sparx.co.uk/deck/fiendish/5.asp">Sparx Deck</a>, the problem is as follows:</p>

<blockquote><p>A basketball player decides to spend an afternoon practicing free throws and recording her performance. Over the first hour, her scoring percentage is less than 75%, but by the end of the session, her overall scoring percentage for the day is more than 75%. Is it necessarily true that at some moment during the session her scoring percentage was exactly 75%?</p></blockquote>

<!-- more -->

<p>The answer to the above problem is <strong>yes</strong>. This may seem counter-intuitive but the reasoning will soon become clear as I was interested in solving the extension:
<blockquote><p>Extension: How special is the choice of 75% in this question? Does the same result hold for other percentages?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>So let us restate the general problem:</p>

<blockquote><p>A basketball player decides to spend an afternoon practicing free throws and recording her performance. Over the first hour, her scoring percentage is less than p%, but by the end of the session, her overall scoring percentage for the day is more than p%. Is it necessarily true that at some moment during the session her scoring percentage was exactly p%?</p></blockquote>

<p>To do this we will prove that the alternative, that the percentage can skip over <em>p</em>%, must be false for some values of <em>p</em> and we will then investigate what decides these values.</p>

<p>First let us express the percentage as a fraction \(p=\frac{a}{b} \times 100\) subject to the constraint \(a&lt;b\) as it is impossible for the scoring percentage to exceed 100%.</p>

<p>If we assume that it is possible to skip over <em>p</em> then there must be some point where the current percentage is less than <em>p</em> but by scoring just one more basket it will exceed <em>p</em>.</p>

<p>If we let <em>B</em> be the number of baskets scored and <em>N</em> be the total number of shots attempted then we can express these requirements as:</p>

<p>\[ \frac{B}{N}&lt;\frac{a}{b} \quad \mathsf{ and } \quad \frac{B+1}{N+1}&gt;\frac{a}{b} \]</p>

<p>These can be re-arranged to give:
\[ bB &lt; aN \]
\[ b(B+1) &gt; a(N+1)  \]</p>

<p>The latter of which can be rearranged to:
 \[bB &gt;aN + a - b\]</p>

<p>Remember we have the constraint that \(a&lt;b\), hence:
 \[aN+a-b &lt; aN\]</p>

<p>Therefore we require that:</p>

<p>\[ aN+a-b &lt; bB &lt; aN\]</p>

<p>As we also require that <em>a</em>, <em>b</em>, <em>B</em> and <em>N</em> are all integers then clearly this can only be satisfied when:
\[ a-b &lt; -1 \]</p>

<p>In any case that \(a-b = -1 \) the scoring percentage will always pass through <em>p</em> if it starts below it and ends up exceeding it.</p>

<p>For example this is the case for \(p=75\%\) as \(a=3\) and \(b=4\) but it is not the case for \(p=60\%\) where \(a=3\) and \(b=5\).</p>

<p>Now we can see why it must pass through 75% and have determined the other percentages for which this condition holds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
