<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Math | In The Aggregate]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexgmcm.github.io/blog/categories/math/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexgmcm.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-14T15:17:39+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexgmcm.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[alexgmcm]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Basket Case]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexgmcm.github.io/blog/2014/11/20/basket-case/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-20T17:22:47+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexgmcm.github.io/blog/2014/11/20/basket-case</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>When you have eliminated the impossible, whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.</p><footer><strong>Sherlock Holmes</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I recently discovered a neat problem while looking at job applications. From the <a href="http://sparx.co.uk/deck/fiendish/5.asp">Sparx Deck</a>, the problem is as follows:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>A basketball player decides to spend an afternoon practicing free throws and recording her performance. Over the first hour, her scoring percentage is less than 75%, but by the end of the session, her overall scoring percentage for the day is more than 75%. Is it necessarily true that at some moment during the session her scoring percentage was exactly 75%?</p></blockquote></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The answer to the above problem is <strong>yes</strong>. This may seem counter-intuitive but the reasoning will soon become clear as I was interested in solving the extension:
<blockquote><p>Extension: How special is the choice of 75% in this question? Does the same result hold for other percentages?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>So let us restate the general problem:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>A basketball player decides to spend an afternoon practicing free throws and recording her performance. Over the first hour, her scoring percentage is less than p%, but by the end of the session, her overall scoring percentage for the day is more than p%. Is it necessarily true that at some moment during the session her scoring percentage was exactly p%?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>To do this we will prove that the alternative, that the percentage can skip over <em>p</em>%, must be false for some values of <em>p</em> and we will then investigate what decides these values.</p>

<p>First let us express the percentage as a fraction \(p=\frac{a}{b} \times 100\) subject to the constraint \(a&lt;b\) as it is impossible for the scoring percentage to exceed 100%.</p>

<p>If we assume that it is possible to skip over <em>p</em> then there must be some point where the current percentage is less than <em>p</em> but by scoring just one more basket it will exceed <em>p</em>.</p>

<p>If we let <em>B</em> be the number of baskets scored and <em>N</em> be the total number of shots attempted then we can express these requirements as:</p>

<p>\[ \frac{B}{N}&lt;\frac{a}{b} \quad \mathsf{ and } \quad \frac{B+1}{N+1}&gt;\frac{a}{b} \]</p>

<p>These can be re-arranged to give:
\[ bB &lt; aN \]
\[ b(B+1) &gt; a(N+1)  \]</p>

<p>The latter of which can be rearranged to:
 \[bB &gt;aN + a - b\]</p>

<p>Remember we have the constraint that \(a&lt;b\), hence:
 \[aN+a-b &lt; aN\]</p>

<p>Therefore we require that:</p>

<p>\[ aN+a-b &lt; bB &lt; aN\]</p>

<p>As we also require that <em>a</em>, <em>b</em>, <em>B</em> and <em>N</em> are all integers then clearly this can only be satisfied when:
\[ a-b &lt; -1 \]</p>

<p>In any case that \(a-b = -1 \) the scoring percentage will always pass through <em>p</em> if it starts below it and ends up exceeding it.</p>

<p>For example this is the case for \(p=75\%\) as \(a=3\) and \(b=4\) but it is not the case for \(p=60\%\) where \(a=3\) and \(b=5\).</p>

<p>Now we can see why it must pass through 75% and have determined the other percentages for which this condition holds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
